<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.1.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-12-29T15:59:29+00:00</updated><id>http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/</id><title>Usman Khaliq</title><subtitle>Coder,Data Science Enthusiast, ICT4D Practitioner.</subtitle><author><name>Usman Khaliq</name><email>usman.khaliq91@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title>We Made it, Mon</title><link href="http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/replug/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We Made it, Mon" /><published>2020-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/replug</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/replug/">&lt;p&gt;While cleaning up my email folder today, I came across this email that I had sent to myself on the 15th of Jan, 2015. It’s always a bittersweet experience to revisit your notes from yonder years, and to reflect on how far you have travelled since then. I slightly chuckle to myself thinking about what was really bothering me when I wrote this, but trying not to be too self-deprecating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;get a grip on yourself. Things arent working out the way you planned them to, but since when has life really been
a basket of roses? You, out of all people, should have realized that. If you want something in life, you need to fight
for it. And everything for you has been a struggle, but so far, you eventually do get what you want and whatever is
best for you right? Why lose hope and become so helpless at this junction?
Everything is not lost, far from it. You know what you really need to do in the next few months. There are loads of
amazing opportunities that you need to work on, instead of letting your head get to you. It is tough, it is difficult,
and it is a constan,relentless battle. But do not lose yourself in a self wallowing ball of pity and leave all of the
hard work that you have done for yourself.
Find that spark in yourself again. Make your sadness, your disappointment, your frustation into a form of inspiration
to start striving harder for what you really want to achieve. You yourself know what you are capable of, do not let
this happen to yourself. And stop falling constantly into that trap of thinking that it is futile, that it is already too
late for you to pick up your game.
Dont do this to yourself. Things will get better, everything will work out fine, find the faith that you have so
dramatically lost over the past few months, and get back to things. Stop overthinking, stop being so hard on yourself.
Go to sleep now. Wake up in a few hours time, study for your exams, reclaim that relentless spark back. The unread emails
and the evernote notes are waiting for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Usman Khaliq</name><email>usman.khaliq91@gmail.com</email></author><summary>While cleaning up my email folder today, I came across this email that I had sent to myself on the 15th of Jan, 2015. It’s always a bittersweet experience to revisit your notes from yonder years, and to reflect on how far you have travelled since then. I slightly chuckle to myself thinking about what was really bothering me when I wrote this, but trying not to be too self-deprecating.</summary></entry><entry><title>Accessing Google Cloud Platform Buckets From a Co-Lab Notebook Running R</title><link href="http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/gcp_colab_r/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Accessing Google Cloud Platform Buckets From a Co-Lab Notebook Running R" /><published>2020-06-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/gcp_colab_r</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/gcp_colab_r/">&lt;p&gt;Last week, I set up a Google Co-lab notebook running on R (my preferred language for data exploration and early stages EDA). I wanted to access some buckets from a Google Cloud Platform(GCP) project that was being hosted on my company’s GCP platform. I used the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;googleCloudStorageR&lt;/code&gt; library written by &lt;a href=&quot;https://code.markedmondson.me/&quot;&gt;Mark Edmondson&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the documentation for the package, they specified downloading a service account JSON file from a GCP project, which would then be referenced by the library for connecting to the GCP project and accessing the buckets. However, since I wanted this notebook to be easily shared by other people across my organization, I did not want to access a JSON file that had the access keys for the API and which would need to be saved along with the Co-lab notebook. Instead, I wanted to connect and authenticate with the GCP project interactively and in real-time from the Co-lab notebook, which would allow anyone with the correct credentials for my organization’s GCP project to run the notebook on their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seemingly simple workaround took longer than I had thought it would. With ample help from Marc, I was able to solve this issue using the code snippet below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;install.packages(&quot;httr&quot;)
install.packages(&quot;R.utils&quot;)
install.packages(&quot;googleCloudStorageR&quot;)
if (file.exists(&quot;/usr/local/lib/python3.6/dist-packages/google/colab/_ipython.py&quot;)) {
  library(R.utils)
  library(httr)
  reassignInPackage(&quot;is_interactive&quot;, pkgName = &quot;httr&quot;, function() return(TRUE))
}
options(
  rlang_interactive = TRUE,
  gargle_oauth_email = &quot;email_address&quot;,
  gargle_oauth_cache = TRUE
)
tt &amp;lt;- gargle::token_fetch(scopes = &quot;https://www.googleapis.com/auth/cloud-platform&quot;)
googleAuthR::gar_auth(token = tt)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Usman Khaliq</name><email>usman.khaliq91@gmail.com</email></author><summary>Last week, I set up a Google Co-lab notebook running on R (my preferred language for data exploration and early stages EDA). I wanted to access some buckets from a Google Cloud Platform(GCP) project that was being hosted on my company’s GCP platform. I used the googleCloudStorageR library written by Mark Edmondson.</summary></entry><entry><title>The transience of life</title><link href="http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/transience-of-life/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The transience of life" /><published>2019-03-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/transience-of-life</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/transience-of-life/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was first publised on my &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@ottoman91/the-transience-of-life-223ff312f28f&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; profile&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A case of bad flu can often send one to a trip down the rabbit hole of 
“thoughts-that-have-been-regularly-pushed-back-at-the-top-of-my-overfilled-mind.” 
I didn’t get much work done this weekend, and while mindlessly scrolling through 
my phone/laptop/tv in the midst of Monday Blues, I kept thinking about young 
people who have departed from this world. I did not personally know any of 
these people that well — at best, they were just random acquaintances at 
university. Now, a part of me wishes that I did know them well, that I had 
known a bit more about their dreams, fears, aspirations in life. I’m not sure 
what I would have done with this information. It’s just that, the idea that 
people who are in their youth can so suddenly disappear from this earth, is a 
bit jarring on some level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We go through so many pre-defined motions every day. We tick off boxes from our 
daily to-do-lists, we have grand plans about what we want to achieve 1,2,5 years
from now, but the hard reality is that none of us have a guarantee on the actual 
time scale that we have to achieve all these things. When our reel of borrowed 
time finally ends, what happens to all the thoughts and plans that we had made 
for ourselves. Do they simply cease to exist, the output of hours of mental 
heavy lifting just disappearing into a non-existing ether? Or are they out 
there somewhere, part of the unified and invisible sub-conscious stream of 
thoughts, ideas, emotions and plans that is and isn’t a part of the collective
human experience? Nobody knows, and perhaps nobody ever will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every human being has or had aspirations at some points in their lives. What
happens when these aspirations aren’t realized? Further yet, are these 
aspirations even supposed to be realized? In our quest for wanting to change
the world and leaving our mark during our brief presence in this universe, 
are we missing out a crucial element on how we should be living and experiencing
life? I guess these questions will keep me up every night until I recover 
from my flu and am able to push them back to the long-term memory cache. I
hope those flu medicines do their magic soon.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Usman Khaliq</name><email>usman.khaliq91@gmail.com</email></author><summary>This post was first publised on my Medium profile</summary></entry><entry><title>Replug</title><link href="http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/the-restart/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Replug" /><published>2018-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/the-restart</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/the-restart/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I wrote this post last September as a reflection essay for my Design and Manufacture class
at Stanford. Reposting this again so that it can serve as a reminder of the things that I 
want to restart doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A blank slate, and the uncertainty that comes with it is something that I have been yearning for 
since the past several years ; a blank slate on which I can shape up my ideas, thoughts and 
combine them with the correct mindset and required skills to truly achieve what I want to in life. 
I was born and raised in Karachi, the largest and arguably the most diverse city of Pakistan. 
Witnessing the city’s stark inequalities while growing up made me aware of how the lottery of 
birth pans out, and since an early age, I felt a nagging sense of doing something meaningful to 
improve the lives of the less fortunate. While studying computer engineering in college, I 
continued to explore the space of design thinking, especially in the context of creating services 
for people at the bottom of the pyramid in the developing world. I developed a working 
prototype for a low cost water purifier in urban areas, and my work was featured by Acumen, an 
impact investment fund that works in Africa, Asia and South America. This exposure enabled me 
to land a job as a computer programmer/researcher/product manager at a startup working in the 
financial inclusion and agriculture technology space in Sierra Leone. Over the next three years, I 
worked on a wide range of projects, ranging from advising the government of Liberia on how to 
make their government processes more data driven and transparent, to piloting an infectious 
disease surveillance system in Sierra Leone, and building a mobile phone based savings product 
for subsistence farmers. At Stanford, I want to improve my design skills and focus towards 
building products and solutions that can improve the delivery of life saving medical care to 
people living in remote areas in Pakistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hobbies are reading, writing, listening to music and street photography, although I have not 
been involved with them as much as I would ideally like to.  On weekends, I can usually be 
found engrossed in my books with a journal nearby, penning down my thoughts on how I 
interpret and perceive different situations. My favourite genres are science fiction, current affairs, 
philosophy and economics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting how life experiences and circumstances end up shaping one’s outlook. Hobbies, 
passions and fortes that were once second nature end up feeling completely alien and foreign, 
which is exactly what happened to me while being away from home for almost seven years due 
to college and work commitments. I listen to way less new music than I used to, I read fewer 
books, and it takes an effort to clearly articulate ideas and thoughts that aren’t technical in nature. 
I also feel a disconnect from the concept of “home”; in some ways I feel that I do not understand 
the people and the place where I am from, frustrated at the general pettiness in thinking and 
narrow-mindedness that is unfortunately present there. At times though, I miss the place and its 
people, and the “inner voice” that is only triggered by a specific place and the memories and 
mental images that one associates with it. I hope that the next two years at Stanford will help me 
to make a hard reset, and rediscover the inner voice that got lost amidst all the mundane activities 
that encapsulate ‘adult life’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Stanford, I want to build a strong design acumen in both physical as well as digital mediums, 
and nurture the skill of translating ideas into tangible prototypes. I am passionate towards using 
human centered design to build products and services that fulfill critical needs of poor people in 
the developing world, and am immensely excited at the intellectual rigor that Stanford would 
provide me to achieve this goal.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Usman Khaliq</name><email>usman.khaliq91@gmail.com</email></author><summary>I wrote this post last September as a reflection essay for my Design and Manufacture class
at Stanford. Reposting this again so that it can serve as a reminder of the things that I 
want to restart doing.</summary></entry><entry><title>SMS is still King in low tech environments</title><link href="http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/sms-is-king/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SMS is still King in low tech environments" /><published>2017-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/sms-is-king</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/sms-is-king/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In this piece,I talk about the science and emotion behind SMS Firebolt, 
an SMS gateway built to democratize information sharing for the poor. I worked
on this project during my time at &lt;a href=&quot;https://idtlabs.xyz&quot;&gt;iDT Labs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/sms1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;this is a placeholder image&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Mobile network coverage still outstrips mobile internet coverage in large 
      rural areas of the region. This, coupled with the low cost of sending SMS, 
      makes it a very attractive medium for building up tech based solutions 
      that aim to solve specific issues in the socio-economic space. 
      [Reference image by Ben Lyon]
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;g-still-the-dominant-technology-in-west-africa&quot;&gt;2G Still the Dominant Technology in West Africa&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the upward trend in smartphone penetration in Sub Saharan Africa 
(expected to reach 80 percent by 2022) in the mostly fragile sub-regional 
block of the Economic Community of West African States (ECOWAS), 2G is still 
the dominant technology, accounting for 90 percent of total mobile connections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With spectrum availability being a challenge in the mass rolling out of 3G and 
4G services, it is important to revisit the inherent assumptions that are 
currently prevalent in the technology for development space of positioning 
an increasing number of products solely on the smartphone medium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;suitability-to-local-contexts&quot;&gt;Suitability to Local Contexts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite often, what gets lost amidst the discussions of using mobile phones for 
augmenting the delivery of essential services is not on the potential of the 
technology itself, but rather, on how applicable it would be in the local context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the deplorable state of education in this region, it would be a stretch 
to claim that the standard of digital literacy holds any better. The great 
chunk of people at the base of the pyramid (BOP) are generally not comfortable 
with using applications on smartphones, which limits the potential of these 
applications to deliver a critical service to the end users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;poor-infrastructure-to-support-smartphones&quot;&gt;Poor Infrastructure to Support Smartphones&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although smartphones are becoming cheaper by the day due to the influx of 
copycat Android devices, it should be noted that most of these devices are 
ill-equipped to smoothly run anything other than the most basic smartphone 
applications, such as a web browser or an instant messaging service. Therefore, 
this calls into question the assumption that the cheaper smartphone devices 
can usher a mass adoption of mobile based products and services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mobile data is generally expensive for the average end users,and is available 
under a pay-as-you-go scheme, thereby forcing the end users to mold their 
internet consumption behavior . This greatly limits the potential of smartphone
 applications to be scaled amongst the end users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also important to understand that in rural areas, people often share cell
 phones, with the younger and more literate members of the community assisting 
 the older community members in everything from making or receiving a call to 
 using mobile money. Generally, smartphone app design is skewed in such a way 
 that the user experience assumes a personalized, one-to-one relationship 
 between a user and his device. Mobile app developers and designers working in 
 the development sector need to appreciate this fact while designing applications 
 that provide a private service to the end users, such as financial credit, on a 
 device which is also actively used by other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-evergreen-benefits-of-plain-text-sms&quot;&gt;The Evergreen Benefits of Plain Text SMS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mobile network coverage still outstrips mobile internet coverage in large 
rural areas of the region. This, coupled with the low cost of sending SMS, 
makes it a very attractive medium for building up tech based solutions that 
aim to solve specific issues in the socio-economic space, since there is a 
high chance that the message is received by the intended recipient at a cost 
that is still manageable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-inherent-challenges-with-building-novel-sms-products-and-services-in-the-region&quot;&gt;The Inherent Challenges with Building Novel SMS Products and Services in the Region&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In spite of the advantages that SMS has, building products and services on top 
of the medium is still a challenge, especially for non-tech savvy organizations 
and individuals. These challenges stem from a number of structural realities 
that exist in the SMS ecosystem, which can be summarized as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is a lack of easy to consume application programming interfaces (APIs) 
in the ecosystem. In laymen terms, APIs are boilerplate codes that allow for 
using the functionality of software systems without having to understand their 
underlying architecture in great detail. The major mobile network operators (MNOs) 
in Sub Saharan Africa usually do not have well documented and publicly available 
APIs that can be used by developers to build up SMS based services . As a result, 
it is difficult for small players and new entrants to create novel ways of 
delivering essential services via the SMS medium.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The general tech skill of individuals in Sub Saharan Africa, in particular 
around building products that perform well in poor connectivity environments 
is low. It is therefore challenging for local players to hire talent which can 
utilize the underlying SMS infrastructure to build new products.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/sms2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;this is a placeholder image&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Photo by Ken Banks, kiwanja.net
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sms-firebolt--an-sms-gateway-built-for-low-tech-environments&quot;&gt;SMS Firebolt : An SMS Gateway Built for Low Tech Environments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keeping in consideration the importance that plain text messages still have as 
an effective mode of communication for any product or service in our part of 
the world, coupled with the inherent difficulty that organizations face in 
incorporating SMS into their offerings, we are currently developing SMS Firebolt, 
an SMS gateway that augments some of the challenges around quickly building 
robust and scalable SMS services via the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By providing a rich set of well documented APIs in a number of popular programming 
languages, such as Java, Python and PHP. These APIs would encourage developers 
to incorporate the gateway into their software products and allow them to send 
SMS alerts to their end customers in various use cases.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By providing a pay-as-you-go service via which organizations can instruct 
our team to send SMS alerts to their end customers at specific events. 
SMS Firebolt has been written in the Spring Java framework, and at the backend 
it is powered by the excellent open source Kannel WAP gateway to send messages 
in real time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SMS Firebolt has been written in the Spring Java framework, and at the backend 
it is powered by the excellent open source &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kannel.org/&quot;&gt;Kannel&lt;/a&gt; 
WAP gateway to send messages in real time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-we-envision-sms-firebolts-critical-usage-in-the-tech-for-development-space&quot;&gt;How We Envision SMS Firebolt’s Critical Usage in The Tech for Development Space&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We would be incorporating SMS Firebolt in a wide range of both, our existing 
products as well as in a number of services that we are currently developing 
in the financial inclusion space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Eazy Bank, our suite of core banking software that is based on the MifosX 
project, is currently being used by a number of micro finance organizations 
(MFIs) in Sierra Leone and Uganda to assist them in streamlining their back 
office operations. By linking it with SMS Firebolt, we would enable MFIs to 
send regular alerts directly on the mobile phones of their end users, most of 
whom exclusively use feature phones. We hope that making crucial information 
more readily accessible to the end users would lead to an uptake in the 
adoption of financial instruments.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are currently in the midst of rolling out the pilot for iCommit, a 
conditional cash savings service that uses mobile money and allows subsistence 
farmers to save money from one harvest season to buy inputs for the next 
growing season. iCommit extensively uses USSD codes and has a plain text 
interface to encourage maximum update amongst the end users. SMS Firebolt 
would be handing the flow of messages between the farmers and the service.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Widespread usage of mobile money in the rural areas of Sierra Leone is still 
a massive challenge. To try and solve this, we are currently developing iAgent,
 a peer-to-peer cash in and cash out service that adopts the “sharing economy” 
 model by allowing individuals to act as mobile money agents at their leisure. 
 iAgent would have both, a smartphone based interface and a USSD based plain text 
 interface. The text message based communication flow of the application would 
 be routed through SMS Firebolt.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-critical-takeaway-lesson-follow-the-occams-razor-in-your-solution&quot;&gt;The Critical Takeaway Lesson: Follow the Occam’s Razor in Your Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tech for development space is filled with horror stories about long delayed
 projects and bloated products that aimed to “change the world”, but often ended 
 up causing some unintended negative externalities. Quite often, technologists 
 working in this space tend to overcomplicate the solution at hand, naively 
 assuming that the power of technology is sufficient to circumvent the structural 
 problems that plague developing and underdeveloped communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality is that technology alone is never a solution; rather, it needs to 
augment existing communication and delivery channels that are working well. 
Despite its age, plain text messages are still critically important for the 
vast majority of people in the world. So the next time you have the urge to 
brainstorm on yet another “app” that will make the world a better place, pause, 
take a step back, and think on how to incorporate your service in less than 
160 plain text characters.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Usman Khaliq</name><email>usman.khaliq91@gmail.com</email></author><summary>In this piece,I talk about the science and emotion behind SMS Firebolt, 
an SMS gateway built to democratize information sharing for the poor. I worked
on this project during my time at iDT Labs</summary></entry><entry><title>An efficient and quick way for removing a Homebrew package and all of its dependencies on macOS</title><link href="http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/homebrew/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An efficient and quick way for removing a Homebrew package and all of its dependencies on macOS" /><published>2017-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/homebrew</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/homebrew/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article was first publised on my &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@ottoman91/an-efficient-and-quick-way-for-removing-a-homebrew-package-and-all-of-its-dependencies-on-macos-32e9eaaffa2d&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; profile&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Homebrew is an excellent command line package management tool for Mac OSx, 
and it is rightly proclaimed as “The missing package manager for macOS”, as stated on its official website. 
However, a few days ago, I came across an urgent task which I had not addressed before, namely, how to 
cleanly and completely remove a package installed from Homebrew, along with all of its dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick online search rendered the following approach on &lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/7323261/uninstall-remove-a-homebrew-package-including-all-its-dependencies&quot;&gt;Stackoverflow&lt;/a&gt;, which included using an 
external command called brew rmtree, which was to be executed as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ brew tap beeftornado/rmtree
$ brew rmtree &amp;lt;package&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, for some reason, when I ran this command, brew took an insanely long 
time to update. I am not quite sure what the error was, but it was most 
probably due to my crappy internet connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, I came across another method for achieving this task on the same 
Stackoverflow answer thread. I found &lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/7323261/uninstall-remove-a-homebrew-package-including-all-its-dependencies/24070232#24070232&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; method to be easier and way quicker, 
although it did take me a while to figure out how to run external brew scripts 
and the configurations that need to be made to run them. To save others the 
hassle and time of understanding how the configuration would need to be set up, 
I am highlighting the steps followed below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Download the brew_clean script from &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/cskeeters/10ff1295bca93808213d&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; Github repo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once you have unzipped the downloaded file, copy the brew_clean script 
to /usr/local/bin. This would ensure that the script is global.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make the script executable by running the following command in the /usr/local/bin directory:
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;
sudo chmod+x brew_clean
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Run the following command in your directory of choice to generate a file 
that contains the list of all brew packages installed on your machine:
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;
brew leaves &amp;gt; brew_packages 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open the brew_packages file using your favourite text editor 
( which is nano in my case for such small tasks). In the file, delete the name 
of the package you want to remove. Save and close the file.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Run the following command to allow brew_clean to remove the package you 
deleted from the brew_packages file:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;brew_clean brew_packages 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there you have it. You can verify that the package has indeed been deleted 
by moving to the /usr/local/Cellar directory. The package that you just deleted 
would no longer be listed in the directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope this helped. Happy coding and creating awesome software solutions for 
the world!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Usman Khaliq</name><email>usman.khaliq91@gmail.com</email></author><summary>This article was first publised on my Medium profile</summary></entry></feed>
