<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.1.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-02-03T01:56:34+00:00</updated><id>http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/</id><title>Usman Khaliq</title><subtitle>Coder,Data Science Enthusiast, ICT4D Practitioner.</subtitle><author><name>Usman Khaliq</name><email>usman.khaliq91@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title>Replug</title><link href="http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/the-restart/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Replug" /><published>2018-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/the-restart</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/the-restart/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I wrote this post last September as a reflection essay for my Design and Manufacture class
at Stanford. Reposting this again so that it can serve as a reminder of the things that I 
want to restart doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A blank slate, and the uncertainty that comes with it is something that I have been yearning for 
since the past several years ; a blank slate on which I can shape up my ideas, thoughts and 
combine them with the correct mindset and required skills to truly achieve what I want to in life. 
I was born and raised in Karachi, the largest and arguably the most diverse city of Pakistan. 
Witnessing the city’s stark inequalities while growing up made me aware of how the lottery of 
birth pans out, and since an early age, I felt a nagging sense of doing something meaningful to 
improve the lives of the less fortunate. While studying computer engineering in college, I 
continued to explore the space of design thinking, especially in the context of creating services 
for people at the bottom of the pyramid in the developing world. I developed a working 
prototype for a low cost water purifier in urban areas, and my work was featured by Acumen, an 
impact investment fund that works in Africa, Asia and South America. This exposure enabled me 
to land a job as a computer programmer/researcher/product manager at a startup working in the 
financial inclusion and agriculture technology space in Sierra Leone. Over the next three years, I 
worked on a wide range of projects, ranging from advising the government of Liberia on how to 
make their government processes more data driven and transparent, to piloting an infectious 
disease surveillance system in Sierra Leone, and building a mobile phone based savings product 
for subsistence farmers. At Stanford, I want to improve my design skills and focus towards 
building products and solutions that can improve the delivery of life saving medical care to 
people living in remote areas in Pakistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hobbies are reading, writing, listening to music and street photography, although I have not 
been involved with them as much as I would ideally like to.  On weekends, I can usually be 
found engrossed in my books with a journal nearby, penning down my thoughts on how I 
interpret and perceive different situations. My favourite genres are science fiction, current affairs, 
philosophy and economics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting how life experiences and circumstances end up shaping one’s outlook. Hobbies, 
passions and fortes that were once second nature end up feeling completely alien and foreign, 
which is exactly what happened to me while being away from home for almost seven years due 
to college and work commitments. I listen to way less new music than I used to, I read fewer 
books, and it takes an effort to clearly articulate ideas and thoughts that aren’t technical in nature. 
I also feel a disconnect from the concept of “home”; in some ways I feel that I do not understand 
the people and the place where I am from, frustrated at the general pettiness in thinking and 
narrow-mindedness that is unfortunately present there. At times though, I miss the place and its 
people, and the “inner voice” that is only triggered by a specific place and the memories and 
mental images that one associates with it. I hope that the next two years at Stanford will help me 
to make a hard reset, and rediscover the inner voice that got lost amidst all the mundane activities 
that encapsulate ‘adult life’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Stanford, I want to build a strong design acumen in both physical as well as digital mediums, 
and nurture the skill of translating ideas into tangible prototypes. I am passionate towards using 
human centered design to build products and services that fulfill critical needs of poor people in 
the developing world, and am immensely excited at the intellectual rigor that Stanford would 
provide me to achieve this goal.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Usman Khaliq</name><email>usman.khaliq91@gmail.com</email></author><summary>I wrote this post last September as a reflection essay for my Design and Manufacture class
at Stanford. Reposting this again so that it can serve as a reminder of the things that I 
want to restart doing.</summary></entry><entry><title>An efficient and quick way for removing a Homebrew package and all of its dependencies on macOS</title><link href="http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/homebrew/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An efficient and quick way for removing a Homebrew package and all of its dependencies on macOS" /><published>2017-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/homebrew</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://ottoman91.github.io/ottoman91/homebrew/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article was first publised on my &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@ottoman91/an-efficient-and-quick-way-for-removing-a-homebrew-package-and-all-of-its-dependencies-on-macos-32e9eaaffa2d&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; profile&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Homebrew is an excellent command line package management tool for Mac OSx, 
and it is rightly proclaimed as “The missing package manager for macOS”, as stated on its official website. 
However, a few days ago, I came across an urgent task which I had not addressed before, namely, how to 
cleanly and completely remove a package installed from Homebrew, along with all of its dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick online search rendered the following approach on &lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/7323261/uninstall-remove-a-homebrew-package-including-all-its-dependencies&quot;&gt;Stackoverflow&lt;/a&gt;, which included using an 
external command called brew rmtree, which was to be executed as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ brew tap beeftornado/rmtree
$ brew rmtree &amp;lt;package&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, for some reason, when I ran this command, brew took an insanely long 
time to update. I am not quite sure what the error was, but it was most 
probably due to my crappy internet connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, I came across another method for achieving this task on the same 
Stackoverflow answer thread. I found &lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/7323261/uninstall-remove-a-homebrew-package-including-all-its-dependencies/24070232#24070232&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; method to be easier and way quicker, 
although it did take me a while to figure out how to run external brew scripts 
and the configurations that need to be made to run them. To save others the 
hassle and time of understanding how the configuration would need to be set up, 
I am highlighting the steps followed below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Download the brew_clean script from &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/cskeeters/10ff1295bca93808213d&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; Github repo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once you have unzipped the downloaded file, copy the brew_clean script 
to /usr/local/bin. This would ensure that the script is global.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make the script executable by running the following command in the /usr/local/bin directory:
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;
sudo chmod+x brew_clean
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Run the following command in your directory of choice to generate a file 
that contains the list of all brew packages installed on your machine:
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;
brew leaves &amp;gt; brew_packages 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open the brew_packages file using your favourite text editor 
( which is nano in my case for such small tasks). In the file, delete the name 
of the package you want to remove. Save and close the file.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Run the following command to allow brew_clean to remove the package you 
deleted from the brew_packages file:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;brew_clean brew_packages 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there you have it. You can verify that the package has indeed been deleted 
by moving to the /usr/local/Cellar directory. The package that you just deleted 
would no longer be listed in the directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope this helped. Happy coding and creating awesome software solutions for 
the world!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Usman Khaliq</name><email>usman.khaliq91@gmail.com</email></author><summary>This article was first publised on my Medium profile</summary></entry></feed>
